Okay, so in this video then,
we're going to be covering
dependencies, activity dependencies,
as well as leads and lags.
Now, dependencies are actually often used
interchangeably with relationships,
right, but there is a difference.
There's a subtle different.
Let's talk about dependencies first time.
Now, there are four types of dependencies,
right?
Four types of dependencies.
You've got mandatory, discretionary, right,
to mention here, external and internal.
So these are, four specific types of
dependencies.
And these are dependencies between an
activity.
Right, you have the relationships,
which is a finish to start, start to
finish, finish to finish
and finish to start,
right, which we discuss
in a previous video.
This one though, in this case,
they're called dependencies.
Again, dependencies are between
activities.
So let's talk about the first one then,
a mandatory dependency.
A mandatory dependency, also known as hard
logic or hard dependency.
You can see either of those terms.
Mandatory, dependency, hard logic or hard
dependency.
And a mandatory basically means that you
have to perform a
certain task a certain way.
Just due to physical limitations,
physical conditions, laws of mathematics,
laws of science, or even just logic, you
have to perform a
certain task a certain way.
So for example, you can't test a system
until you've built the system.
If you don't have the system built,
what are you going to test?
You have to build something before you can
test it.
Or when you're building a house,
you have to dig the foundations
before you can frame,
before you can put up the roof.
You can't decide, you know, all right,
let's just start building this house.
We're first going to build the roof.
Let's complete the roof.
Then we'll dig the foundations.
And then we'll start framing.
No, you have to dig the foundations first.
then you have to frame, then you can put
up the roof.
It's a mandatory dependency.
Those activities are mandatory, they are
mandatory dependent upon one another.
Now, contracts also fall as a mandatory,
right.
Contracts are also a mandatory dependency,
right, because you're contractually
obligated to perform a task or perform a
task in a certain sequence.
Discretionary dependency, on the other
hand, also known as soft logic,
or preferred logic or arbitrary logic.
And discretionary then is entirely up to
us when we want to run our activities.
We can move activities around however we
want to.
It's entirely up to us.
It's at our discretion, hence the name
discretionary dependency.
Like I said, also known as soft logic or
preferred or arbitrary.
So once we've completed the house,
we first want to do that.
to paint the upstairs of the house,
then we'll paint the downstairs,
then we'll paint the outside.
But if you want to move those activities
around, can easily move them around.
Maybe we'll do the downstairs first
instead of the upstairs.
So that is soft logic, that's
discretionary.
Now the preferred logic
is that we may have a
preference of when we
want to run those activities.
We may have a preference, right?
So we prefer to do the upstairs first.
We prefer to paint the upstairs of the
house first.
And then we'll paint the downstairs and
then we'll paint the outside.
But again, if needed, we can move
activities around.
There's nothing saying that we have to do
the upstairs first and
then the downstairs.
There's nothing saying that we have to do
it in that particular order.
It's not a mandatory dependency.
It's discretionary.
It's up to us.
We can move sequences.
We can re-sequence however we want to.
So these are two types, mandatory
discretionary.
The other two then are external and
internal.
So external dependency.
An external dependency is
a dependency outside of the
project team and generally
outside of the team's control.
And usually third parties, such as
vendors.
Vendor, you know, we're dependent on a
vendor supplying us with raw materials.
If they delay shipment
of raw materials, you
know, we don't really
have any control over that.
We are dependent on them.
That's an external dependency.
Government compliance as well.
That would be considered an external
dependency.
So, for example, you're building a house.
We can't start until we get a permit.
We can't start until we get a permit from
our local government, local authority,
municipality, depending on where you live.
We can't move forward until we get a
permit.
So that would be an external dependency.
And then an internal dependency is
dependencies within the project team,
within the project team's control.
So for example, this activity can only be
performed by one team member.
So we have to wait for that
one team member to be available
in order for them to be
able to perform this activity.
But we have some control over that.
Maybe we can move some of those other
activities around that this team member is
responsible for so that they can start
working on this activity first.
So that's an internal dependency.
It's within the team's control.
It's within the project team's control and
its dependencies within the team itself.
Now, be very careful because an internal
dependency is dependent
by the team itself.
is dependencies within the team itself.
Be very careful with internal and
external.
And internal dependency
is dependencies within
the team itself or
within the team's control.
Not necessarily dependencies within the
organization.
So for example, then, if we are waiting on
data from another division within our
organization and that division is not part
of our project team, we have no control
over the work of that division
or this department, then that
would be an external dependency,
because we have no control.
So an external is not just third parties,
right?
And I mean, obviously it is third parties,
but not just third parties.
An external dependency is
basically any dependencies
that is outside of the
project team, right?
And internal dependencies, specifically
dependencies within the team itself.
So these are four dependencies then.
You have mandatory, discretionary,
external and internal.
So you can have mandatory external,
mandatory internal, right?
And then discretionary, external,
external, external, internal, internal.
Oh, you know, external, mandatory,
external discretionary, internal,
mandatory, internal discretionary.
Now those were the dependencies.
So now let's talk about
leads and lags, because
again, leads and lags
occur between activities.
So a lead basically means starting your
activity earlier.
So you're speeding up successor
activities.
So items that you
plan to run sequentially,
you're now going to run them in parallel.
So you've got activity A and activity B.
B is dependent on activity A.
Once activity A finishes, then you can
start activity B.
However, in order to
reduce a schedule, right, why
do we start activity B
before we finish activity A?
We'll run them in parallel.
So there's a little bit of overlap.
So in this case then, we have a two-day
lead.
Where you see FS, FS means finish to
start.
That's the relationship.
right.
So A and B have a finish to start
relationship.
We finish A before we can start B.
However, since we want to start our
activity earlier, since we want to reduce
the schedule a little bit earlier,
let's start B two days earlier.
So B then, so now we have a two-day lead.
So that's where the FS minus two means.
It's a finish to start minus two.
We can start B two days earlier.
So that's reduced the schedule by two
days.
So that is what a lead refers to.
Now, you can only do this if there is a
discretionary dependency.
If there's a mandatory dependency, you
have to finish A before you can start B.
There's not much we can do about that.
It's only if it's a discretionary
dependency.
And then the other term is lag,
and the lag is an imposed delay.
An imposed delay on the
schedule, and an imposed
delay meaning it's
inbuilt into the schedule.
Not a delay meaning that we've gone behind
schedule.
It's already inbuilt.
We already know about it.
It's inbuilt as part of our project
schedule overall.
So for example, again, you're building a
house.
You pour concrete into your foundations.
Well, as soon as you pour concrete, you
can't necessarily start framing, right?
You have to wait for
the concrete to cure, to
settle, harden, right,
before you can start framing.
So that may just, that may take,
for example, seven days, and I'm just
making up that number,
I'm not construction guy or
anything, I'm just making
up this number, right?
We pour concrete down, let's leave it for
seven days before we can start framing.
That seven days would be considered a lag.
And that seven days is
not, you know, a delay
meaning they've gone behind the schedule.
No, it's already been built into the
schedule.
And that's what this FS plus seven refers
to.
Again, FS finished to start.
We finish pouring the concrete before we
can start framing.
But we have to wait seven days.
And it's plus seven.
So that's increased our schedule by seven
days.
So now, again, not meaning that we're,
going behind schedule by seven days it's
already inbuilt our schedule will take
into consideration this lag of seven days
okay so a couple of
uh important terms there
as well uh for you for
the uh for the pmp exam